So raise your hand if you know someone
إرفعو أيديكم إذا كنتم تعرفون أحدا
in your immediate family or circle of friends
من العائلة أو دائرة الأصدقاء
who suffers from some form of mental illness.
يعاني من مرض عقلي
Yeah. I thought so. Not surprised.
نعم ، ليس أمرا مفاجئا ، لقد اعتقدت ذلك
And raise your hand if you think that
حسنا، ارفعوا أيديكم إذا اعتقدتم
basic research on fruit flies has anything to do
أن بحثا على ذباب الفاكهة له علاقة
with understanding mental illness in humans.
بفهم المرض العقلي لدى الإنسان
Yeah. I thought so. I'm also not surprised.
لقد اعتقدت ذلك تماما
I can see I've got my work cut out for me here.
استطيع أن أرى أنني أفقد عملي الآن
As we heard from Dr. Insel this morning,
وكما سمعنا من الدكتور "إنسل" هذا الصباح
psychiatric disorders like autism, depression and schizophrenia
الإضطرابات النفسية مثل الإكتئاب، والفصام ،ومرض التوحد
take a terrible toll on human suffering.
تحدث آثارا رهيبة على النفس الإنسانية
We know much less about their treatment
لازلنا لانعرف سوى القليل عن علاجها
and the understanding of their basic mechanisms
وآلية تأثيرها
than we do about diseases of the body.
والتأثيرات الجسدية المصاحبة لها
Think about it: In 2013,
تخيلوا ذلك : في عام ٢٠١٣
the second decade of the millennium,
العقد الثاني من الألفية
if you're concerned about a cancer diagnosis
وقد ساورك الشك بشأن الإصابة بالسرطان
and you go to your doctor, you get bone scans,
فذهبت للطبيب ، وأجريت مسحا للعظام
biopsies and blood tests.
وتحليلا للخلايا، واختباراً للدم
In 2013, if you're concerned about a depression diagnosis,
في ٢٠١٣: إذا ساورك الشك حول الإصابة بأعراض الإكتئاب
you go to your doctor, and what do you get?
وذهبت للطبيب ، عندها مالذي ستحصل عليه؟
A questionnaire.
إستبيان
Now, part of the reason for this is that we have
ذلك بسبب أن لدينا
an oversimplified and increasingly outmoded view
نظرة تبسيط عفا عليها الزمن
of the biological basis of psychiatric disorders.
للأساس البيولوجي للإضطرابات النفسية
We tend to view them --
والتي نميل لعرضها
and the popular press aids and abets this view --
في الصحافة على أنها خلل كيميائي فسيولوجي كالإيدز
as chemical imbalances in the brain,
لكن في الحالة النفسية تكون خلل في التوازن الكيميائي للدماغ
as if the brain were some kind of bag of chemical soup
كما لو كان الدماغ كيس حساء كيميائي
full of dopamine, serotonin and norepinephrine.
مليئة بالسيروتونين،و الدوبامين والنورادرينالين
This view is conditioned by the fact
هذه النظرة تدعم تلك الحقيقة
that many of the drugs that are prescribed to treat these disorders,
وهي أن العديد من الأدوية التي توصف لعلاج الأعراض النفسية
like Prozac, act by globally changing brain chemistry,
كالبروزاك ، تعمل عن طريق التغيير في كيميائية الدماغ
as if the brain were indeed a bag of chemical soup.
كما لو كان الدماغ بالفعل كيس حساء كيميائي
But that can't be the answer,
لكن هذا لايمكن أن يكون الجواب
because these drugs actually don't work all that well.
لأن هذه الأدوية في الواقع لاتعمل بشكل مثالي
A lot of people won't take them, or stop taking them,
الكثير من الأشخاص سيتوقفون عن تناولها ، أو لن يتناولوها على الإطلاق
because of their unpleasant side effects.
بسبب الأضرار الجانبية لها
These drugs have so many side effects
هذه الأدوية لها الكثير من الأضرار الجانبية
because using them to treat a complex psychiatric disorder
لأن استخدامها لعلاج اضطرابات نفسية معقدة
is a bit like trying to change your engine oil
تماما مثل تغيير زيت السيارة
by opening a can and pouring it all over the engine block.
بفتح العلبة وسكبها فوق المحرك
Some of it will dribble into the right place,
القليل منه سينسكب في المكان الصحيح
but a lot of it will do more harm than good.
لكن الكثير سيسبب الفوضى بدلا عن تحسين الوضع
Now, an emerging view
وجهة النظر الناشئة الآن
that you also heard about from Dr. Insel this morning,
والتي سمعتم عنها من الدكتور إنسل هذا الصباح
is that psychiatric disorders are actually
وهي أن الإضطرابات النفسية في الواقع هي
disturbances of neural circuits that mediate
اضطرابات الدوائر العصبية
emotion, mood and affect.
العاطفة والمزاج والشعور
When we think about cognition,
عندما نتحدث عن الإدراك
we analogize the brain to a computer. That's no problem.
فإننا نقيس الدماغ بجهاز الكمبيوتر ، لامشكلة في ذلك
Well it turns out that the computer analogy
وقد تبين أن هذا القياس
is just as valid for emotion.
ينطبق أيضا على العاطفة
It's just that we don't tend to think about it that way.
إلا أننا لانميل للتفكيربها بهذا الشكل
But we know much less about the circuit basis
لذا لانعرف الكثير عن عن أساس هذه الدوائر
of psychiatric disorders
من الإضطرابات النفسية
because of the overwhelming dominance
بسبب هيمنة
of this chemical imbalance hypothesis.
فرضية الخلل في التوازن الكيميائى
Now, it's not that chemicals are not important
حسنا، هذا لايعني أن الكيميائيات الدماغية ليست مهمة
in psychiatric disorders.
في الإضطرابات العصبية
It's just that they don't bathe the brain like soup.
إلا أنها لاتسبح في الدماغ بعشوائية كالحساء
Rather, they're released in very specific locations
بل هي تنطلق في مواقع محددة جداً
and they act on specific synapses
وتعمل على نقاط عصبية دقيقة
to change the flow of information in the brain.
لتغير تدفق المعلومات في الدماغ
So if we ever really want to understand
لذا إذا أردنا الفهم الفعلي
the biological basis of psychiatric disorders,
للأساس البيولوجي للإضطرابات النفسية
we need to pinpoint these locations in the brain
علينا تحديد تلك المواقع في الدماغ
where these chemicals act.
التي تنشط فيها تلك الكيميائيات
Otherwise, we're going to keep pouring oil all over our mental engines
عدا ذلك، سنظل نسكب الزيت بشكل عشوائي على ذلك المحرك الدماغي
and suffering the consequences.
ونعاني الأضرار الجانبية لذلك
Now to begin to overcome our ignorance
الآن ، ولنتغلب على نقص معرفتنا
of the role of brain chemistry in brain circuitry,
بدور كيمياء الدماغ على الدوائر العصبية
it's helpful to work on what we biologists call
من المفيد أن نعمل على مايدعوه علماء الأحياء
"model organisms,"
"نموذج الكائنات الحية"
animals like fruit flies and laboratory mice,
حيوانات مثل فئران المختبرات وذباب الفاكهة
in which we can apply powerful genetic techniques
حيث يمكن تطبيق تقنيات وراثية قوية
to molecularly identify and pinpoint
لنحدد وبدقة
specific classes of neurons,
ونصنف فئات من الخلايا العصبية
as you heard about in Allan Jones's talk this morning.
كما ذكر دكتور آلن جونز هذا الصباح
Moreover, once we can do that,
عندما نحقق ذلك
we can actually activate specific neurons
سيكون بإمكاننا تنشيط خلايا عصبية محددة
or we can destroy or inhibit the activity of those neurons.
والقضاء على أخرى ومنع نشاطها
So if we inhibit a particular type of neuron,
فإذا تم إيقاف نشاط خلايا معينة
and we find that a behavior is blocked,
سنجد أننا استطعنا إيقاف السلوك
we can conclude that those neurons
إذا نستنتج أن هذه الخلايا العصبية
are necessary for that behavior.
مهمة لذلك السلوك
On the other hand, if we activate a group of neurons
وعلى الجانب الآخر، عندما ننشط مجموعة من تلك الخلايا
and we find that that produces the behavior,
ونجد تأثيرا سلوكيا لذلك
we can conclude that those neurons are sufficient for the behavior.
نستنتج أن هذه الخلايا ضرورية لذلك السلوك
So in this way, by doing this kind of test,
بهذا الشكل ، وبإجراء هذا النوع من الإختبارات
we can draw cause and effect relationships
يمكن رسم العلاقة بين السبب والنتيجة
between the activity of specific neurons
بين نشاط خلية عصبية محددة
in particular circuits and particular behaviors,
في دائرة عصبية معينة وسلوك معين
something that is extremely difficult, if not impossible,
وهو أمر غاية في الصعوبة، إن لم يكن من المستحيل
to do right now in humans.
إجراؤه الآن على الإنسان
But can an organism like a fruit fly, which is --
لكن هل يمكن لكائنات مثل ذبابة الفاكهة والتي تعد
it's a great model organism
نموذجا رائعا
because it's got a small brain,
وذلك لأن لها دماغا صغيرا
it's capable of complex and sophisticated behaviors,
وقادرة على السلوكيات المعقدة والمتطورة
it breeds quickly, and it's cheap.
إنها تتكاثر بسرعة ، ورخيصة
But can an organism like this
لكن هل يمكن لكائن مثل هذا
teach us anything about emotion-like states?
أن يعلمنا شيئا عن الأوضاع العاطفية؟
Do these organisms even have emotion-like states,
هل لهذه الكائنات أوضاع عاطفية أساساً
or are they just little digital robots?
أم أنها مجرد روبوتات رقمية صغيرة؟
Charles Darwin believed that insects have emotion
"تشارلز داروين" كان يعتقد أن للحشرات مشاعر
and express them in their behaviors, as he wrote
وتعبر عنها عن طريق السلوك ، كما كتب ذلك
in his 1872 monograph on the expression of the emotions in man and animals.
في دراسة له عام ١٨٧٢ في التعبير عن المشاعر لدى الأنسان والحيوان
And my eponymous colleague, Seymour Benzer, believed it as well.
زميلي "سايمور بينزر" يعتقد ذلك أيضا
Seymour is the man that introduced the use of drosophila
سيمور هو أول من استخدم ذبابة الفاكهة
here at CalTech in the '60s as a model organism
في الستينات الميلادية بإعتبارها النموذج الحي في معهد كاليفورنيا للتكنلوجيا
to study the connection between genes and behavior.
لدراسة العلاقة بين الجينات والسلوك
Seymour recruited me to CalTech in the late 1980s.
وظفني سيمور في المعهد في ؛أواخر الثمانينات
He was my Jedi and my rabbi while he was here,
لقد كان عرابي ومرشدي
and Seymour taught me both to love flies
وعلمني أن أحب الذباب
and also to play with science.
وأن ألعب مع العلم
So how do we ask this question?
إذا ، كيف نطرح ذلك السؤال؟
It's one thing to believe that flies have emotion-like states,
هل للذبابة مشاعر
but how do we actually find out whether that's true or not?
وكيف نتأكد ماإذا كان ذلك صحيح فعلا، أم لا؟
Now, in humans we often infer emotional states,
لدى البشر،غالبا ما نستدل علي الحالة العاطفية
as you'll hear later today, from facial expressions.
من تعابير الوجه
However, it's a little difficult to do that in fruit flies.
وهذا بالطبع أمر صعب مع ذبابة الفاكهة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's kind of like landing on Mars
إن الأمر يبدو مثل الهبوط على المريخ
and looking out the window of your spaceship
والنظر من نافذة المركبة الفضائية
at all the little green men who are surrounding it
لكل أولئك الرجال الخضر الصغار الذين يحيطون بالمركبة
and trying to figure out, "How do I find out
ومحاولة اكتشاف
if they have emotions or not?"
فيما إذا كانت لهم مشاعر أم لا؟
What can we do? It's not so easy.
ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل ؟ إنه ليس بالأمر السهل
Well, one of the ways that we can start
لكن أحد الطرق التي يمكننا أن نبدأ بها
is to try to come up with some general characteristics
هو محاولة التوصل لبعض الخصائص العامة
or properties of emotion-like states
أو خصائص الإنفعالات العاطفية
such as arousal, and see if we can identify
مثل الرغبة ، ونرى ما إذا يمكننا ملاحظة
any fly behaviors that might exhibit some of those properties.
السلوكيات التي قد تُظهرها الذبابة
So three important ones that I can think of
لذا، فالعناصر الثلاثة التي يمكنني التفكير فيها
are persistence, gradations in intensity, and valence.
هي الإستمرارية، ‎التدرج في الشدة ، والتكافؤ الجوهري
Persistence means long-lasting.
الإستمرارية تعني الديمومة
We all know that the stimulus that triggers an emotion
جميعنا يعلم أن الحافز الذي يُطلق المشاعر
causes that emotion to last long after the stimulus is gone.
يؤدي إلى بقاء الشعور لفترة حتى بعد زوال التحفيز
Gradations of intensity means what it sounds like.
التدرج في المشاعر يعني مايبدو
You can dial up the intensity or dial down the intensity of an emotion.
أنه يمكنك رفع شدة العواطف أو تخفيضها
If you're a little bit unhappy, the corners of your mouth
فلو كنت غير سعيد إلى حد ما فإن زوايا الفم
turn down and you sniffle,
تميل للأسفل ، مع استنشاق الهواء بشدة
and if you're very unhappy, tears pour down your face
وفي حال غيرسعيد تماما، ستنزل الدموع من عينيك
and you might sob.
وقد تتنهد
Valence means good or bad, positive or negative.
التكافؤ يعني الجودة أو السؤ، الإيجاب أو السلب
So we decided to see if flies could be provoked into showing
لذا قررنا أن نرى ماإذا كان ممكنا إثارة الذباب ليُظهر
the kind of behavior that you see
نوعا من السلوك الذي يمكننا ملاحظته
by the proverbial wasp at the picnic table,
مثل ذلك السلوك الذي تلاحظه من الدبور حول طاولة النزهه
you know, the one that keeps coming back to your hamburger
ذلك الذي يستمر في العودة للنيل من البرجر خاصتك
the more vigorously you try to swat it away,
وكلما حاولت أن تبعده
and it seems to keep getting irritated.
يبدو أنه يستمر في العودة بشكل مزعج ويبدوا أكثر إصرارا
So we built a device, which we call a puff-o-mat,
لذا، قمنا ببناء آلة أسميناها آلة النفخ
in which we could deliver little brief air puffs to fruit flies
والتي تمكننا من نفخ الهواء بخفة على ذباب الفاكهة
in these plastic tubes in our laboratory bench
في أنابيب الإختبار البلاستيكية الموجودة لدينا في المختبر
and blow them away.
أو نفخها بشدة
And what we found is that if we gave these flies
وقد وجدنا أنه في حالة أثرنا على هذه الذبابات
in the puff-o-mat several puffs in a row,
بعدة نفخات
they became somewhat hyperactive
سيؤدي بها بشكل أو بآخر لفرط في الحركة
and continued to run around for some time after the air puffs actually stopped
وتستمر بالدوران لبعض الوقت حتى بعد توقف النفخات
and took a while to calm down.
وتستغرق فترة من الوقت لتهدأ
So we quantified this behavior
لذا قمنا بقياس هذا السلوك بشكل كمي
using custom locomotor tracking software
باستخدام برامج تتبع حركة متخصصة
developed with my collaborator Pietro Perona,
قام بتطويرها مساعدي "بيترو بيرونا"
who's in the electrical engineering division here at CalTech.
والذي يعمل في ‎ شعبة الهندسة الكهربائية في معهد كاليفورنيا للتكنولوجيا
And what this quantification showed us is that,
وقد أظهرت لنا تلك القياسات مايلي
upon experiencing a train of these air puffs,
بتجربة إطلاق سلسلة من النفخات
the flies appear to enter a kind of state of hyperactivity
يدخل الذباب في حالة فرط في الحركة
which is persistent, long-lasting,
لمدة ليست بالقصيرة
and also appears to be graded.
وتبدو التأثيرات متدرجة
More puffs, or more intense puffs,
فبإزدياد عدد النفخات وشدتها
make the state last for a longer period of time.
نجد أن حالة فرط الحركة تزداد شدة وتدوم لوقت أطول
So now we wanted to try to understand something
هنا نريد أن نفهم
about what controls the duration of this state.
من المسؤول عن مدة استمرارية هذه الحالة
So we decided to use our puff-o-mat
لذا قررنا استخدام آلة النفخ
and our automated tracking software
وبرنامج تتبع الحركة المتخصص
to screen through hundreds of lines of mutant fruit flies
لتصوير مئات من ذباب الفاكهة المعدل وراثيا
to see if we could find any that showed abnormal responses to the air puffs.
ونرى ماإذا كان أي منها سيظهر ردات فعل مختلفة عن الغالبية
And this is one of the great things about fruit flies.
وهذا أحد الأشياء الرائعة بشأن ذباب الفاكهة
There are repositories where you can just pick up the phone
حيث توجد تلك المستودعات التي يمكنك ومن خلال مكالمة هاتفية
and order hundreds of vials of flies of different mutants
طلب المئات من ذباب الفاكهة المختلفة والمعدلة جينيا
and screen them in your assay and then find out
ومراقبتهم في المختبر ومعرفة
what gene is affected in the mutation.
الجين المسؤول عن ذلك التغير
So doing the screen, we discovered one mutant
وبالفحص والتتبع ، لاحظنا أحد الذبابات المعدلة جينيا
that took much longer than normal to calm down
تستغرق وقتا أطول للعودة لحالتها الطبيعية
after the air puffs,
بعد تأثير نفخات الهواء
and when we examined the gene that was affected in this mutation,
وعند اختبار الجين المسؤول عن تلك الطفرة
it turned out to encode a dopamine receptor.
وجدنا أنه يشير إلى مُستقبلات الدوبامين
That's right -- flies, like people, have dopamine,
نعم، هذا صحيح، الذباب كما الإنسان لديه دوبامين
and it acts on their brains and on their synapses
والذي يعمل على أدمغته ونقاط إلتقاء الأعصاب لديه
through the same dopamine receptor molecules
‎من خلال نفس جزيئات مستقبلات الدوبامين
that you and I have.
تلك التي توجد لدي ولديك
Dopamine plays a number of important functions in the brain,
‎ يلعب الدوبامين عددا من الوظائف الهامة في الدماغ
including in attention, arousal, reward,
التي من ضمنها الإهتمام، المكافأة، والإثارة،
and disorders of the dopamine system have been linked
‎ وقد تم ربط الإضطرابات في نظام الدوبامين
to a number of mental disorders including drug abuse,
‎بعدد من الاضطرابات النفسية بما في ذلك إدمان المخدرات
Parkinson's disease, and ADHD.
مرض باركنسون ، واضطرابات فرط الحركة وتشتت الإنتباه
Now, in genetics, it's a little counterintuitive.
الآن في علم الوراثة
We tend to infer the normal function of something
نميل للإستدلال على الوضع الطبيعي للشيء
by what doesn't happen when we take it away,
عن طريق ملاحظة غياب الأعراض بغياب مؤثر
by the opposite of what we see when we take it away.
بواسطة معرفة العكس لما نراه
So when we take away the dopamine receptor
لذا فعندما نستبعد مستقبلات الدوبامين
and the flies take longer to calm down,
ويستغرق الذباب وقتا أطول للهدوء والعودة للوضع الطبيعي بعد النفخ
from that we infer that the normal function of this receptor and dopamine
نستنتج أن هذه هي الوظيفة الطبيعية لمستقبلات الدوبامين
is to cause the flies to calm down faster after the puff.
هي أن تجعل الذباب يهدأ بشكل أسرع بعد نفخ الهواء
And that's a bit reminiscent of ADHD,
وهذا يذكرنا بحالات فرط الحركة وتشتت الإنتباه
which has been linked to disorders of the dopamine system in humans.
‎والتي تم ربطها باضطرابات نظام الدوبامين في البشر
Indeed, if we increase the levels of dopamine in normal flies
‎بالطبع ، إذا قمنا بزيادة مستويات الدوبامين في الذباب العادي
by feeding them cocaine
بإطعامها الكوكايين
after getting the appropriate DEA license
بالطبع بعد الحصول على الرخصة من إدارة مكافحة المخدرات
— oh my God -- (Laughter) —
ياإلهي (ضحك)
we find indeed that these cocaine-fed flies
سنجد في الواقع أن هذه الذبابات التي أعطيت الكوكايين
calm down faster than normal flies do,
تهدأ بشكل أسرع من الذباب الطبيعي
and that's also reminiscent of ADHD,
وهذا يذكرنا بإضطرابات فرط الحركة وتشتت الإنتباه
which is often treated with drugs like Ritalin
والتي غالبا ماتُعالج بأدوية مثل الريتالين
that act similarly to cocaine.
والذي يعمل على غرار الكوكايين
So slowly I began to realize that what started out
وببطئ بدأت أدرك مابدأت به
as a rather playful attempt to try to annoy fruit flies
وأن تلك المحاولات الهزلية لإزعاج ذباب الفاكهة
might actually have some relevance to a human psychiatric disorder.
أصبح لها علاقة حقيقية ومهمة بالإضطرابات النفسية لدى الإنسان
Now, how far does this analogy go?
كيف يمكن أن نشرح هذا التجانس ؟
As many of you know, individuals afflicted with ADHD
كما يعلم الكثير منكم ، أن الأشخاص المصابين باضطرابات فرط الحركة وتشتت الإنتباه
also have learning disabilities.
يعانون من صعوبات في التعلم
Is that true of our dopamine receptor mutant flies?
‎ هل هذا ينطبق على الذباب المعدل جينيا ؟
Remarkably, the answer is yes.
الأمر الملفت فعلا ، أنه ينطبق
As Seymour showed back in the 1970s,
كما أظهر ذلك سيمور في السبعينات الميلادية
flies, like songbirds, as you just heard,
الذباب ، تماما كالطيور المغردة
are capable of learning.
قابل للتعلم
You can train a fly to avoid an odor, shown here in blue,
يمكنك تدريب الذبابة على الطيران وتجنب الرائحة كما هو موضح هنا بالأزرق
if you pair that odor with a shock.
حيث إذا زاوجت تلك الرائحة بصدمة
Then when you give those trained flies the chance to choose
ثم أعطيت هذه الذبابات المدربة الفرصة للإختيار
between a tube with the shock-paired odor and another odor,
بين أنبوب الرائحة المترافق مع صدمة وأنبوب آخر
it avoids the tube containing the blue odor that was paired with shock.
ستجده يتجنب الأنبوب الذي يحوي رائحة مترافقة مع صدمة
Well, if you do this test on dopamine receptor mutant flies,
لكن في حال إجراء هذا الإختبار على الذباب المعدل جينيا المستقبل للدوبامين
they don't learn. Their learning score is zero.
سنجد أن معدل التعلم لديه صفر، إنه لايتعلم
They flunk out of CalTech.
لقد أخفق وسيطرد من ‎معهد كاليفورنيا للتكنولوجيا
So that means that these flies have two abnormalities,
وهذا يعني أن لهذا الذباب حالتين من الحالات الغير طبيعية
or phenotypes, as we geneticists call them,
أوكما ندعوها نحن علماء الوراثة "ظواهر"
that one finds in ADHD: hyperactivity and learning disability.
وهي : فرط الحركة ، وعدم القدرة على التعلم
Now what's the causal relationship, if anything, between these phenotypes?
‎الآن ما هي العلاقة السببية بين هذه الظواهر؟
In ADHD, it's often assumed that the hyperactivity
الفرضية الغالبة أن فرط الحركة مسبب لتشتت الإنتباه
causes the learning disability.
وصعوبة التعلم
The kids can't sit still long enough to focus, so they don't learn.
الطفل لايمكنه الجلوس بالقدر الذي يمكنه من التركيز وبالتالي القدرة على التعلم
But it could equally be the case that it's the learning disabilities
لكن إحتمالية أن تكون صعوبة التعلم
that cause the hyperactivity.
هي السبب في تشتت الإنتباه ممكنة بالقدر نفسه
Because the kids can't learn, they look for other things to distract their attention.
ولأن الطفل لايمكنه التعلم فهو يبحث عما يشتت انتباهه
And a final possibility is that there's no relationship at all
والإحتمال الأخير هو أن لايكون هناك أي علاقة
between learning disabilities and hyperactivity,
بين الظاهرتين على الإطلاق
but that they are caused by a common underlying mechanism in ADHD.
‎لكن المسبب آلية أساسية مشتركة في أعراض فرط الحركة و تشتت الإنتباه
Now people have been wondering about this for a long time
يتساءل الناس عن ذلك لفترة طويلة
in humans, but in flies we can actually test this.
في البشر، لكن في الذباب فبالطبع يمكن إختبار ذلك
And the way that we do this is to delve deeply into the mind
‎و الطريقة للقيام بذلك هو عن طريق الخوض عميقا في عقل
of the fly and begin to untangle its circuitry using genetics.
الذبابة والبدء بتفكيك الدوائر العصبية باستخدام علم الوراثة
We take our dopamine receptor mutant flies
حيث نقوم بأخذ الذبابات المعدلة جينيا
and we genetically restore, or cure, the dopamine receptor
‎    ونقوم بمعالجة أو استبدال مستقبلات الدوبامين وراثيا
by putting a good copy of the dopamine receptor gene
‎و وضع نسخة جيدة من الجينات مستقبلات الدوبامين
back into the fly brain.
‎ في دماغ الذبابة
But in each fly, we put it back only into certain neurons
‎  ولكن في كل ذبابة نقوم بالعملية على خلايا عصبية معينة
and not in others, and then we test each of these flies
مختلفة عن الأخرى، ومن ثم نختبر كل واحدة من هذه الذبابات
for their ability to learn and for hyperactivity.
من ناحية القدرة على التعلم وفرط الحركة
Remarkably, we find we can completely dissociate these two abnormalities.
‎بشكل ملحوظ ، وجدنا أنه يمكننا فصل هاتين الظاهرتين تماما
If we put a good copy of the dopamine receptor back
‎إذا وضعنا نسخة جيدة من مستقبلات الدوبامين
in this elliptical structure called the central complex,
في ذلك الهيكل البيضاوي والمسمى المركز
the flies are no longer hyperactive, but they still can't learn.
لن يكون لدى الذباب فرطا في الحركة لكنه مازال غير قادر على التعلم
On the other hand, if we put the receptor back in a different structure
ومن ناحية أخرى ، إذا وضعنا مستقبلات الدوبامين في موضع آخر
called the mushroom body,
يدعى مجسم الفطر
the learning deficit is rescued, the flies learn well,
نجد أن الذباب يكون قادرا عن التعلم
but they're still hyperactive.
لكن فرط الحركة مازال قائما
What that tells us is that dopamine
وهذا يخبرنا أن الدوبامين
is not bathing the brain of these flies like soup.
لايسبح في الدماغ بعشوائية
Rather, it's acting to control two different functions
بل إنه يسيطر على وظيفتين مختلفتين
on two different circuits,
في منطقتين مختلفتين من الدماغ
so the reason there are two things wrong with our dopamine receptor flies
لهذا السبب هناك خللين في مستقبلات الدوبامين في الذباب
is that the same receptor is controlling two different functions
وذلك لأن المستقبلات تسيطر على وظيفتين مختلفتين
in two different regions of the brain.
في موضعين مختلفين من الدماغ
Whether the same thing is true in ADHD in humans
وسواء كان الشيء نفسه ينطبق على البشر أم لا
we don't know, but these kinds of results
لانعلم حتى الآن، لكن مثل هذه النتائج
should at least cause us to consider that possibility.
‎تفتح لنا الباب للنظر في هذا الإحتمال
So these results make me and my colleagues more convinced than ever
‎ هذه النتائج تجعلني وزملائي أكثر اقتناعا من أي وقت مضى
that the brain is not a bag of chemical soup,
أن الدماغ ليس كيس حساء كيميائي
and it's a mistake to try to treat complex psychiatric disorders
ومن الخطأ علاج ‎ الاضطرابات النفسية المعقدة
just by changing the flavor of the soup.
فقط عن طريق تغيير نكهة الحساء
What we need to do is to use our ingenuity and our scientific knowledge
‎و ما يتعين علينا القيام به هو استخدام إبداعنا ومعرفتنا العلمية
to try to design a new generation of treatments
‎في محاولة تصميم جيل جديد من العلاجات
that are targeted to specific neurons and specific regions of the brain
تستهدف خلايا عصبية محددة ومناطق محددة من الدماغ
that are affected in particular psychiatric disorders.
تكون مؤثرة ‎على اضطرابات النفسية خاصة
If we can do that, we may be able to cure these disorders
إذا استطعنا معالجة هذه الإضطرابات
without the unpleasant side effects,
بدون إحداث أضرار جانبية
putting the oil back in our mental engines,
سنكون قد وضعنا الزيت في المكان الصحيح المحدد له في المحرك
just where it's needed. Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا